A Guide to the Records of the Virginia Tech University Libraries, 1925-2006
Special Collections, Virginia Tech
Special Collections, Virginia Tech
Records of the Virginia Tech University Libraries, 1925-2006
Special Collections, Virginia Tech, Blacksburg, Va.
RG 23
173.8 Cubic Feet 205 boxes
This collection includes minutes, correspondence, meeting notes, and more from departments, committees, and individuals in the Virginia Tech University Libraries.
Bechanan, H. Gordon
Brown, Ralph Minthorne
Gherman, Paul M.
Hitchingham, Eileen
Robb, Seymour, 1901-1961
Rudolph, Gerald A.
Shirk, Frank
Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University. University Libraries
Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University. University Libraries. Special Collections Department
Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University. University LIbraries. Collections and Technical Services (CTS)
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Accruals
Additional materials will be added to the finding aid as they are received and processed.
Acquisition Information
The Records of the Virginia Tech University Libraries was transferred to Special Collections. Additional items were transferred to Special Collections in August 2019.
Historical Note
When the college began in 1872, V.E. Shepherd was appointed as librarian (as well as treasurer, secretary of the faculty and Board of Visitors, and to teach foreign languages). The library started with 500 volumes, which were primarily gifts from congressmen, publishers, and government agencies. Students supervised the library from 1875 until Mary Lacy was appointed as the first full-time librarian in 1903. She was followed by her sister, Ethel Lacy, from 1910-13, and then Eleanor Jones, 1913-23. After two years of acting librarians, Ralph M. Brown was appointed in 1925 and served until 1946. He was succeeded as director by Seymour Robb (1947-61), Frank Shirk (1961-70), Gerald Rudolph (1970-74), Gordon Bechanan (1974-84), Paul Gherman (1985-92), Joanne Eustis (interim, 1992-94), and Eileen Hitchingham (1995-2011). Tyler Walters began his term as Dean of the University Libraries in 2011.
The first branch library was established in 1907 in Agriculture Hall (now Price). In 1955, a new building was opened and named for Carol M. Newman, a professor of English at Virginia Tech for 38 years. At that time, two branch libraries (Agriculture and Engineering) and about twenty departmental collections closed and were integrated into the main collection. During Rudolph's tenure, two new branches were created: Geology (1972) and one in Reston, Virginia, for the Northern Virginia Graduate Program.
Scope and Content
The University Archives contains a large volume of the records of the University Libraries. This collection continues to grow on almost a daily basis. Records of each department within the library, committees, taskforces, the faculty association, and the staff association are included in this collection. Since the records of past library directors are central to this collection, their descriptions are given below.
Click here for a box-level inventory of these materials.
Arrangement
The collection is divided by RG subgroup number.
Adjunct Descriptive Data
Separated Materials
The University Archives also holds newspaper clippings, publications, annual reports, and photographs concerning the library, which have been separated to the Rare Books Collection, Virginia Tech Buildings Architectural Collection, RG 6/3/2e, Record Group Vertical Files, and Historical Photograph Collection.
Index Terms
Subjects:
University Archives; University History
Organizations:
Virginia Agricultural and Mechanical College and Polytechnic Institute; Virginia Polytechnic Institute; Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University; Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University. University Libraries; Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University. University Libraries. Special Collections Department
Contents List
Click here for a box-level inventory of these materials.
- RG 23 - Virginia Tech University Libraries, 69.6 Cubic Feet; 84 boxes (Box 1-84)
- RG 23/1 - Virginia Tech Office of the Dean of the University Libraries
  - RG 23/1/1 - Ralph M. Brown, Library Director, Records, 1925-1947, 0.8 Cubic Feet; 2 boxes (Box 1-2)
    Biographical Note
    Ralph Minthorne Brown was appointed as librarian in 1925. During his tenure, the library collection doubled in size. Brown retired in 1946.
    Scope and Content
    This collection includes budget material (1943-52), statistics (1928-45), proposed library plans (1935-40), Library Committee material (1925-26), and correspondence (1925-47).
    Related Materials
    Brown's personal papers can be found in manuscript collection Ms70-002.
  - RG 23/1/2 - Seymour Robb, Library Director, Records, 1947-1961, 0.6 Cubic Feet; 2 boxes (Box 1-2)
    Seymour Robb succeeded Brown in 1947. In an effort to correct some of the deficiencies of the library, Robb called for a library survey. Funds were received in 1949 for a survey to be conducted by Maurice Tauber of Columbia University Library School and William Jesse of the University of Tennessee Library. Their conclusions led to immediate improvement in funding for the library. Beginning in 1951, funds were sought from various sources for the construction of a new library building. Carol M. Newman Library was completed in 1955. After fourteen years of service, Robb died in office in 1961.
    This collection includes correspondence (1947-61), the Library Survey (1949), and records relating to the construction of Newman Library.
  - RG 23/1/3 - Frank Shirk, Library Director, Records, 1955-1970, 4.2 Cubic Feet; 3 boxes (Box 1-3)
    Frank Shirk assumed the duties of head of the library upon Seymour Robb's death in 1961. Shirk had been with the library since 1948 and had been Associate Library Director since 1955. Accomplishments of his tenure included an increased book budget, beginnings of automation, and adoption of the Library of Congress classification system to replace the Dewey Decimal system. Shirk stepped down in 1970.
    This collection contains budget material (1961-70), gifts and memorial funds (1960-71), Library Committee minutes (1962-70), Library Committee self-study reports and memoranda (1966-68), memoranda to faculty (1964-68), policy statements (1965-69), VPI Interschool Library Committee report (1961), and correspondence dealing with the VPI Archives (1949-70). Also included are the correspondences of the Associate Library Director (Frank Shirk, 1955-61, and Robert Stephenson, 1964-70).
  - RG 23/1/4 - Gerald A. Rudolph, Library Director, Records, 1970-1974, 2.8 Cubic Feet; 2 boxes (Box 1-2)
    Gerald Rudolph became Library Director in 1970. Accomplishments of his administration included: creation of a subject-divisional organization for the library with separate reference desks for science, social sciences, and humanities; formation of two branch libraries (Geology and Northern Virginia); and approval of an addition to Newman Library.
    This collection includes annual reports (1970-72), budget material (1970-72), correspondence (1970-74), Daily Bulletin Notices (1970-71), various committee reports (1970), memoranda concerning automated library system (1971), questionnaires on library (1969-70), student surveys and reports on library system (1971), organizational charts and policy revisions (1970), and correspondence and reports of Dr. Stuart Forth (Library Consultant, 1970). Also included are: State Council of Higher Education Library Advisory Committee material (1968-70); Report of the Subcommittee for Renovation and Addition to the Library (13 October 1970); "A Research Proposal Submitted to Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University" by G.A. Rudolph and M.H. Agee; "The Redesign of Technical Services for Carol M. Newman Library" by G.W. Creasy, W.L. Root, and A.G. Yates (submitted 6 March 1972).
  - RG 23/1/5 - H. Gordon Bechanan, Library Director, Records, 1974-1984, 27.4 Cubic Feet; 21 boxes (Box 1-21)
    H. Gordon Bechanan became Library Director in 1974, after serving as an Assistant Director since 1972. Accomplishments during his tenure included: expansion of the microforms and rare books and manuscripts collections; the library's involvement in several cooperative projects with other research libraries; the library's membership in the Association of Research Libraries and SOLINET; construction of an addition to Newman; and development of an on-line catalog (VTLS). Bechanan retired in 1984.
    This collection includes annual reports (1974-84), budget material (1970-85), building plans for addition to Newman (1970-71), Chemistry Branch Library proposal, Council on Library Resources material (1972-84), items concerning space (1973-80), VPI audits (1978-84), branch libraries policies (1971-82), Manuscript Committee materials, and VTLS materials. Also included are materials dealing with the American Library Association (1951-83), Association of Research Libraries (1976-84), Association of Southeastern Research Libraries (1976-83), Southern College and University Libraries statistics, SCHEV, and Virginia Libraries Association (1971-79).
  - RG 23/1/6 - Paul Gherman, Library Director and University Librarian, Records, 1985-1991, 10.6 Cubic Feet; 9 boxes (Box 1-9)
    Paul M. Gherman became Library Director in 1985. In 1991 the title of the position was changed to University Librarian. Gherman stepped down from the position in 1992.
    This collection includes correspondence (1985-91), Library Administrative Council minutes (1989-90), minutes and literature about the International Archive of Women in Architecture (1989-90), memos and reports of the Association for Research Libraries (1985-89), the University Libraries Stategic Plan (1985), and memos from various departments within the Libraries.
  - RG 23/1/7 - Eileen Hitchingham, Dean of the University Libraries, Records, 2.6 Cubic Feet; 4 boxes (Box 1-4)
    Eileen Hitchingham served as Dean of the University Libraries from 1995 until her retirement on February 1, 2011.
- RG 23/3 - VTLS Operations Group Minutes, c. 1984-1989, 3.8 Cubic Feet; 6 boxes (Box 1-5)
- RG 23/4 - Virginia Tech Northern Virginia Center Resource Center Records, c. 1975-1985, 0.4 Cubic Feet; 1 box (Box 1)
- RG 23/6/1 - Virginia Tech University Libraries Albania Project, 0.4 Cubic Feet; 1 box (Box 1)
  Historical Note
  In the early 1990s, the Virginia Tech University Libraries had an employee exchange with a university in Albania.
- RG 23b/1 - Virginia Tech Newman Library Renovations and Additions Records, c. 1978-1981, c. 2004-2006, 1.5 Cubic Feet; 4 boxes (Box 1-4)
  Virginia Tech's Carol M. Newman Library was opened in 1955. An addition was added in 1981. Another major renovation was completed in 2009.
  These records contain files related to the 1981 renovation and addition as well as renovations made in the mid-2000s.
- RG 23c - Virginia Tech Library Faculty Association Records, c. 1990-1991, 3.6 Cubic Feet; 4 boxes (Box 1-4)
  Scope and Contents
  These records contain the files of the Virginia Tech Library Faculty Association Records and its presidents.
  - RG 23c/1 - Virginia Tech Library Faculty Association's Faculty Affairs Committee Records, 0.4 Cubic Feet; 1 box (Box 1)
- RG 23dd - Virginia Tech Friends of the University Libraries Records, 0.8 Cubic Feet; 2 boxes (Box 1-2)
- RG 23f - Virginia Tech University Libraries Self Study, 1975-1976, 1.4 Cubic Feet; 1 box (Box 1)
- RG 23g - Virginia Tech University Libraries Departmental Annual Reports 1991-1992, 0.2 Cubic Feet; 1 box (Box 1)
- RG 23h - Virginia Tech University Libraries Committees and Departments Records, 2.6 Cubic Feet; 4 boxes (Box 1-4)
  - RG 23h/1a - Virginia Tech Library Council Minutes, 1970-1985, 3 Cubic Feet; 5 boxes (Box 1-5)
  - RG 23h/2 - Virginia Tech Library Administrative Committee Records, 1975-1992, 1.2 Cubic Feet; 3 boxes (Box 1-3)
    Library Administrative Committee was formerly University Libraries Management Committee and formerly Library Advisory Council.
    - RG 23h/2a - Library Administrative Committee Minutes and University Library Bulletins, c. 1991-1995, 0.8 Cubic Feet; 2 boxes (Box 1-2)
  - RG 23h/4 - Virginia Tech University Libraries' Advisory Committees Records, 3.4 Cubic Feet; 6 boxes (Box 1-6)
    These records contain records from the Virginia Tech University Libraries' Advisory Committees on professional development, InterLibrary Cooperation, and LOCAS.
  - RG 23h/6 - Virginia Tech University Libraries' Reference Division Records, c. 1975-1980, 1 Cubic Feet; 3 boxes (Box 1-3)
    - RG 23h/6/1 - Virginia Tech Special Collections Records, c. 1970s-1980s, 4.2 Cubic Feet; 6 boxes (Box 1-6)
      This collection contains registers and permission forms, which may be restricted, and the files of Glenn McMullen, Tamara Kennelly, and Stephen Zietz.
    - RG 23h/6/2 - Virginia Tech University Libraries' Humanities/Social Sciences Reference Department Records, 2.8 Cubic Feet; 2 boxes (Box 1-2)
  - RG 23h/7 - Virginia Tech University Libraries' Technical Services Department Records, 0.8 Cubic Feet; 2 boxes (Box 1-2)
    This collection contains the records of the Virginia Tech University Libraries' Technical Services Department, including Staff Affairs Committee and Bibliographic Services Supervisors Meeting.
    - RG 23h/7a - Virginia Tech University Libraries' Binding and Preparations Department Records, c. 1973-1976, undated, 0.8 Cubic Feet; 2 boxes (Box 1-2)
      This collection contains minutes and index for the Preparation Section Supervisors meetings and records for the Public Relations Task Force.
    - RG 23h/7b - Virginia Tech University Libraries' Cataloging Department Records, c. 1957-1983, 3.4 Cubic Feet; 6 boxes (Box 1-6)
      This collection contains cataloging manuals, statistics, indeces, Cataloging Committee on Committees annual reports, and serials information.
  - RG 23h/8/1 - Virginia Tech University Libraries' CFS/LOCAS Cataloging Systems Records, 12.4 Cubic Feet; 11 boxes (Box 1-11)
  - RG 23h/9 - Virginia Tech University Libraries' Acquisitions Department Records, 1971-1980, 4.4 Cubic Feet; 6 boxes (Box 1-6)
  - RG 23h/12 - Virginia Tech University Libraries' Library Automation Services Department Records, c. 1995-1996, 0.8 Cubic Feet; 2 boxes (Box 1-2)
    This collection contains materials related to online search databases, CFS, TULIP project, and librarian Dave Beagle.
  - RG 23h/13 - Virginia Tech University Libraries' Personnel Services Records, 1.4 Cubic Feet; 1 box (Box 1)